Guide to the Elfriede Abbe papers, 1840-2010.
Abbe, Elfriede papers, 1840-2010.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Elfriede Abbe papers, 1840-2010.
13-7-1102
Elfriede Martha Abbe, 1919-
4.9 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, calendars, catalogs, manuscripts, notes, prints, sketches, pamphlets, mimeographed typescripts, news articles, and printing equipment.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of professional papers; letters concerning a piece of her sculpture, "The Hunter," and the publication of an article on her work; photographs of her and her sculpture; appointment calendars with descriptions of her work, photographs of her works; a catalog of her sculpture; wood cut illustrations, materials for books she illustrated; sketches; wood engraving blocks; announcements of publications of her books and of her gallery shows; typescripts of lectures given; and news articles on her works of art.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Elfriede Abbe, a sculptor, printer, printmaker, and scientific illustrator, received a Bachelor of Fine Arts from Cornell University in 1940 and worked as an artist for the University from 1942-1974.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of professional papers, including correspondence with persons and organizations commissioning her sculpture, suppliers of sculpture materials and casting firms, and from the publisher of her books, collectors of her books and prints, and other artists and craftsmen, admirers and well wishers, and organizations of which she was a member; also, letters concerning a piece of her sculpture, "The Hunter," on display at the 1939 World's Fair and the publication of an article on her work in American Artist in 1962; photographs of her and her sculpture; appointment calendars, annotated with descriptions of her work, methods, and activities, and including photographs of her works, 1978-1988; a catalog of her sculpture; wood cut illustrations, notes, manuscripts and page proofs for books she illustrated, printed, or translated; sketches; wood engraving blocks; prints; pamphlets; announcements of publications of her books; mimeographed typescripts of lectures given; news articles on her works of art; and announcements concerning her gallery shows. Also, a catalog from the Southern Vermont Art Center's 60th Anniversary Festival of the Arts, 1989, and correspondence related to the National Geographic Society Centennial (1988). Also paper with watermark from Dard Hunter and a Broadside printed by Jim Tyler for Elfriede Abbe's 70'th birthday, 1989.
Includes an annotated copy of The Sculpture of Elfriede Abbe; professional correspondence, 1940-2012, with Cornell Library staff and others; a holiday letter from James, Mary, and John Sumner, 1947; personal letters from Erika Pignatti, 1961-1987; a letter from Herbert Finch relating to Mary Bovier; correspondence, newsletter relating to the Abbe Museum in Bar Harbor, Maine; programs and invitations; and miscellaneous biographical materials and clippings.
Also included in the collection are Abbe family papers which consist mainly of the letters (1840-1883) of Elfriede Abbe's great-grandparents, George Waldo Abbe, pioneer of meteorology and climatology and founder of the United States Weather Bureau, and Charlotte Colgate Abbe. The letters refer to concerts and lectures, opinions and incidents relating to abolition, Baptists, New Versionists, the depression of 1857, and summer visits by Charlotte Abbe and the children to "Dog Hill," Moses Cleveland Abbe's farm in South Windham, Connecticut. These letters are printed in a book annotated by Elfrieda Abbe, Letters of George Waldo Abbe and Charlotte Colgate Abbe, 1840-1883, a copy of which is in the collection. Other material consists of biographical and visual material related to Cleveland Abbe and Cleveland Abbe, Junior, particularly a large series of photographs of a European trip in 1901 by Cleveland Abbe, Jr., and photographs and other items relating to her mother Frieda Dauer Abbe.
Correspondents include Charlotte Colgate Abbe, George Waldo Abbe, Talitha Abbe, William Colgate Abbe, Harriet Allen, Edgar Anderson, Stanley Brogren, Knox F. Burnett, Cornelia Van A. Chapin, Gilmore D. Clarke, Theodore R. Dudley, Ettl Studios, John Folinsbee, Roscoe Guernsey, J.L. Hautman, Katherine Thayer Hobson, Carleton Howe, Roy A. Hunt, Arthur Jones, Norman Kent, Irvin Kerlan, Alison Mason Kingsbury, Knight and Son Metal Letters and Figures, Carolyn and Lewis Knudson, Robert D. Kohn, George H.M. Lawrence, Walter Leuba, J. Ben Lieberman, Paul Manship, Ivan Meštrović, James L. Montague, Minnie and Walter C. Muenscher, Hobart Nichols, Richard Pennington, The Rachel McMasters Miller Hunt Botanical Library, Lilly and Felix Reichmann, Roman Bronzeworks, Lessing Rosenwald, Ross W. Sloniker, Lieselotta and Friedrich Solmsen, Alice and Rolla Tryon, Vermarco Lime Company, Vermont Marble Company, S. F. Vorhees, James Lamar Weygand, and Wheeler Williams.
Wood panel carving titled "Edge of the Pond"; Mahogany sculpture of Ptolemy displayed in Reference Room of Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections
SUBJECTS
Names:
Abbe, Elfriede Martha, 1919-; Anderson, Edgar.; Brogren, Stanley.; Burnett, Knox F.; Chapin, Cornelia Van A.; Clarke, Gilmore D., 1892-; Dudley, T. R. (Theodore R.), 1936-; Folinsbee, John Fulton, 1892-1972.; Guernsey, Roscoe.; Hautman, J. L.; Hobson, Katherine Thayer.; Howe, Carleton.; Hunt, Roy A.; Jones, Arthur, 1889-1979.; Kent, Norman, 1903-1972.; Kerlan, Irvin.; Kingsbury, Alison Mason, b. 1898.; Knudson, Carolyn.; Knudson, Lewis, 1884-1958.; Kohn, Robert D., 1870-1953.; Lawrence, George Hill Mathewson, 1910-; Leuba, Walter, 1902-; Lieberman, J. Ben.; Manship, Paul, 1885-1966.; Meštrović, Ivan, 1883-1962.; Montague, James L.; Muenscher, Minnie Worthen.; Muenscher, Walter Conrad Leopold, 1891-1963.; Nichols, Hobart.; Pennington, Richard.; Reichmann, Felix, 1899-; Reichmann, Lilly, 1909-; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979.; Sloniker, Ross W.; Solmsen, Friedrich, 1904-; Solmsen, Lieselotte.; Tryon, Alice F.; Tryon, Rolla Milton, 1916-; Vorhees, S. F.; Weygand, James Lamar.; Williams, Wheeler, 1897-1972.; Cornell University.; Ettl Studios.; Knight and Son Metal Letters and Figures.; Roman Bronzeworks.; Vermarco Lime Company.; Vermont Marble Company.
Subjects:
Art.; Sculpture.; Artists.; Printers.; Printmakers.; Sculptors.; Women artists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Sketches.; Insignias.; Photographs.; Woodcuts.; Illustrations.; Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dard Hunter watermark on sheet of paper and envelope, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- The Rachel McMasters Miller Hunt Botanical Library, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Harriet Allen correspondence, 1921-1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
- Diary of trip to Europe, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Diary of trip to Europe, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "An Artist Looks at the Georgics" - summary, drafts of purpose of essay (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Talks by Elfriede Abbe, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Walter Conrad Muensche" - reprint, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Receipts and bills (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Certificates, 1957, 1965, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous: newsletters, announcements, articles, releases, exhibit catalogs, invitations (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
- Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Photographs - Elfriede Abbe at sculpting work (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Photograph - Abbe at printing work (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Portraits of Elfriede Abbe (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
- 60th Anniversary - Festival of the Arts, Manchester, Vermont, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- George Waldo Abbe and Charlotte Colgate Abbe correspondence, 1840-1850 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- George Waldo Abbe and Charlotte Colgate Abbe correspondence, 1851-1855 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- George Waldo Abbe and Charlotte Colgate Abbe correspondence, 1857-1903 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Cleveland Abbe biographical material, 1916-1917, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Cleveland Abbe, Jr. account books; biographical material, 1895-1900, 1931, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Journal of European trip - geological notes and sketches, and expense account of Cleveland Abbe, Jr., 1902 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Abbe biographical information (Box 3, Folder 7)
- National Geographic Society Centennial, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Tata, Hungary - Count Tege von Konkoly, ca. 1909-1914 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Two portfolio covers for Abbe letters given to Cleveland Abbe, Jr. by Harriet Colgate Abbe, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Abbe miscellany (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Albrecht Penck, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Abbe family - Cleveland Abbe (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Includes Cleveland Abbe's 1901 US Passport for trip to Pulkova Observatory
- Cleveland Abbe photos and 1922 passport, ca. 1898-1922 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Frieda Dauer Abbe, 1903-1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Abbe family, ca. 1903 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Misc. programs, certificates, articles, 1884-1944 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Correspondence re: Letters of George Waldo Abbe and Charlotte Colgate Abbe, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Volume - Letters of George Waldo Abbe and Charlotte Colgate Abbe, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- William Colgate Abbe correspondence, 1852-1867 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- William Colgate Abbe correspondence, 1870-1879 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Talitha Abbe correspondence, 1856, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Photograph of Cleveland Abbe, Jr. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Photograph of Cleveland Abbe, Jr., 1898 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Photographs (2) of Mrs. Cleveland Abbe, Jr., 1905 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Photograph of Mrs. Cleveland Abbe, Jr. and Elfriede Abbe, ca. 1921 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Photograph of Ernst Cleveland Abbe and parents, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photograph of Dog Hill Road (Moses Cleveland Abbe's farm estate was called Dog Hill) (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Photograph of Mt. Abbe, Johns Hopkins Fiord, Glacier Bay, Alaska, named for Cleveland Abbe, Jr. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Photograph of decorations of the U.S. Geological Survey for Roosevelt inauguration, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Photograph of Prof. and Mrs. Cleveland Abbe (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Daguerreotype of William Colgate Abbe, ca. 1860s (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Daguerreotype of Talitha Waldo Abbe (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Daguerreotype of Moses Cleveland Abbe (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Mr. and Mrs. Cleveland Abbe, Dr. and Mrs. Cleveland Abbe, Jr., "Aunt Harriet", ca. 1903-1908 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Hand-colored lantern slide of Charlotte Colgate Abbe (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Photograph of George Waldo Abbe (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Photograph of Ernst C. Abbe (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Photograph and news clipping of Mary "Aunt Mollie" O'Toole, godmother of Elfriede Abbe (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Photographs re: Elfriede Abbe (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Photograph of Walter Conrad Muenscher plaque (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Photographs of family and friends (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Original wood engravings which were reproduced as illustrations for Plants of Virgil's Georgics (3 matted prints in map case) (Box 6, Folder 1)
- The Georgics of Virgin - English translation (Box 6, Folder 2)
- The Plants of Virgil's Georgics - page proofs, notes, etc. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- The Plants of Virgil's Georgics - draft (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Christmas Card 1954 - wood engraving (Box 6, Folder 5)
- 3 matted prints (Box 7)
- 3 original prints (Box 7)
- 1 blueprint of location and pedestal for sculpture "The Hunter" by Elfriede Abbe, 1939 (Box 7)
- Wood engraving titled “Stronghold”, pictures from “The Revelation of St. John the Divine” panels, pencil sketch of mother and self-portrait (Box 7)
- Certificates and awards, 1939-1985 (Box 7)
- Photographs taken in Europe by Cleveland Abbe, Jr., 1901 (Box 8)
- Volume - Garden Spice and Wild Pot-Herbs, 1955 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous catalogs and publications (Box 10)
- Elfriede Abbe engagement books (11), 1978-1988 (Box 11)
- 6 wood printing blocks (Box 12)
- 3 framed prints (Box 12)
- Printing block: Seal of Gardner, Maine (Box 12)
- pictures of art work with correspondence, 1970-2008 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Abbe Museum (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Letters, student project (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Art (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Publications with art (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Exhibitions (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Programs, etc. (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Magazines (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Swann Galleries (Box 13, Folder 9)
- City of Carcassonne (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Clippings (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Biographical information and clippings, 1972-1997 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Invitations, programs, etc, 1978-1994 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Abbe Museum, 1980-2001 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Professional correspondence, 1940-1960 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Professional correspondence, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Professional correspondence, 1980's (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Professional correspondence, 1990's (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Professional correspondence, 2000's (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Professional correspondence, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Letter regarding Mary Bovier, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Pignatti, Erika and Sandro, 1961-1987 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Sumner letter, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 12)
- "Valley Forge" loss, 1968-1985 (Box 14, Folder 13)
- "The Sculpture of Elfriede Abbe" (annotated) (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Folder of Ivan Mestrovic letters in MSS file (Box 26)
- Broadside of Geoffry Chaucer's prologue to "Tales of Canterbury", printed by J. Tyler for Elfriede Abbe's 70'th birthday, in MSS file, 1989 (Box 46)
- Mahogany sculpture of Ptolemy, by Elfriede Abbe, displayed in Reference Room of Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, MU-1313
- Wood panel carving "Edge of the Pond", by Elfriede Abbe, MU-1314